{"tossups": [{"question": "A duchy of this name was ruled by a monarch nicknamed \u201cLongsword\u201d and founded by his father, Rollo. A woman named Emma hailed from this region and married Ethelred the Unready. A duke of this region wed Matilda of Flanders and launched an invasion that culminated in the 1066 Battle of Hastings and conquest of Anglo-Saxon England. For ten points, name this region of north France, the home of William the Conqueror.", "answer": "<b> Normandy</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Mount Fortress was built to protect members of this religion.<em> Fumi-e</em> were pictures that members of this religion stepped on to prove innocence. Twenty-six members of this religion were executed after their protection was revoked by the Shimazu clan. \u201cHidden\u201d members of this religion revolted in the Shimabara Rebellion. This religion was banned by sakoku law in Japan. For ten points, name this religion that was spread to Qing China by Jesuit missionaries.", "answer": "Roman<b> Catholic</b>ism (prompt on Christianity)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "At one battle in this location, General Hemu lost his eye to an arrow, leading to his defeat by Bairam Khan and a 13-year old Akbar. Ahmad Shah and the Durrani Empire won a later battle at this location. Another victory at this site led to the fall of the Dehli Sultanate under Ibrahim Lodi and the rise of Babur. For ten points, name this location of three prominent battles, in 1526, 1556, and 1761 in India, the first of which established the Mughal Empire.", "answer": "Battle(s) of<b> Panipat</b> (prompt on India before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This leader argued that \u201cthe prospect of domination of the nation\u2019s scholars by Federal employment [...] is gravely to be regarded.\u201d This man delivered a \u201cmessage of leave-taking and farewell\u201d that explained\u201cAmerican makers of plowshares could [...] make swords as well\u201d and warned against the military-industrial complex. For ten points, name this 20th century President whose advice regarding the defense industry derived from his service as Allied Commander in World War II.", "answer": "Dwight D.<b> Eisenhower</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A Syrian holder of this position took it at age 14, was plagued by numerous sex scandals, and was assassinated at age 18. In addition to Elagabalus, an earlier holder of this position mocked legislators by suggesting his horse Incitatus could serve as consul; that man was nicknamed \u201clittle boots\u201d and was assassinated by the Praetorian Guard. For ten points, name this position held by madmen like Caligula.", "answer": "<b> Emperor of Rome</b> (prompt on partial answers, like \u201cemperor\u201d or \u201cruler of Rome;\u201d do not accept king of Rome)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man met his business partner, Phineas Miller, while staying at the Mulberry Grove estate of Revolutionary War widow Catherine Greene. He received a government contract to produce ten thousand muskets in two years, during which he pioneered the use of replaceable parts in gun manufacturing. This man developed a machine that used a wire mesh to isolate seeds from the fibers of a crop widely grown in the American south. For ten points, name this inventor of the cotton gin.", "answer": "Eli<b> Whitney</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This political faction was opposed by the White League and the Red Shirts, paramilitary groups that supported the Redeemers. This faction passed legislation that created five districts, each ruled by a different general. Anticipating the dismissal of War Secretary Edwin Stanton, this faction passed the Tenure of Office Act. Thaddeus Stevens led, for ten points, what Reconstruction-era political faction that tried to impeach Andrew Johnson?", "answer": "<b> Radical Republican</b>s (prompt on Republicans)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This body of water, also known as Lago Cochibola, contains a namesake population of freshwater sharks. The first registered Spanish settlement in mainland North America, Granada, is on its shores. The Bryan-Chamorro Treaty gave the US rights to build a canal through this lake, a proposal recently revived by an Hong Kong consortium. For ten points, name this largest lake in Central America, connected by the Tipitapa River to Lake Managua, found in a country also home to the Contras and Sandinistas.", "answer": "Lake<b> Nicaragua</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This government was served by Nathalie Lemel\u2019s Women\u2019s Union. Members of this government destroyed the Vend\u02c6ome Column on the orders of the artist Gustave Courbet [core-bay]. Adolphe Thiers [tee-air] ordered Marshal MacMahon to violently end this government during the Bloody Week. Karl Marx argued that this government was an example of the dictatorship of the proletariat. For ten points, name this socialist government that, after the loss of the Franco-Prussian War, briefly ruled from the French capital.", "answer": "<b> Paris Commune</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This city joined a conflict when its rival attempted to besiege Potidaea, violating the Thirty Years\u2019Peace. Under Lysander, this city\u2019s fleet successfully set up an ambush at Aegospotami; this city\u2019s fleet had also aided Syracuse against the Sicilian Expedition, launched by the Delian League. In 404 BC, this city overthrew democratic rule in their vanquished enemy after winning the Peloponnesian War. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state whose well-trained army subjugated Athens.", "answer": "<b> Sparta</b> (or<b> Lacedaemon</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. An attempt at this action in Smolensk involved plastic explosives disguised as two bottles of brandy. The Reserve Army was activated after one attempt of this action, though its commander, Friedrich Fromm, turned on former ally Friedrich Olbricht. A bomb set off at the Wolf\u2019s Lair nearly performed this action. Claus von Stauffenberg\u2019s Operation Valkyrie called for, for ten points, what action that would have decapitated the Third Reich?", "answer": "<b> assassinating</b> Adolf<b> Hitler</b> (accept equivalents; accept Operation<b> Valkyrie</b> or the<b> July 20</b> plot after \u201cReserve Army\u201d is said; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cremoving Hitler from power\u201d or\u201ckilling Nazis\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In Beijing in April 2013, this non-Asian country\u2019s leader insisted he would send troops to back a hypothetical US invasion of North Korea. This country\u2019s recently-resigned Prime</b> <b>Minister, John Key, had been elected in 2008 over long time Labour leader (+)</b> <b>Helen</b> <b>Clark. Kyle Lockwood designed the proposed \u201cSilver Fern\u201d flag for this country, an option in a failed March 2016 referendum to replace this country\u2019s current flag, which features the (*) </b> Union Jack and Southern Cross. For ten points, name this country in Oceania whose cities include Wellington and Auckland.", "answer": "<b> New Zealand</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man was accused of working with John van Vossen and Robert Rose in aiding the Cherokees, a charge that prompted him to beat accuser William Stanberry with a cane. He was replaced by (+) Mirabeau Lamar in his highest post after he refused to lend support to the Confederacy. During a revolution against (*)</b> Mexican rule, this man masterminded a victory over Santa Anna at San Jacinto. For ten points, name this first president of the Texan Republic, honored as the namesake of Texas\u2019 most populous city.", "answer": "Sam<b> Houston</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This event was the subject of a painting by Karl Briullov that became the basis for a novel by Edward Bulwer-Lytton. This event was discussed in a letter written from Misenum and addressed to (+) Tacitus. This event preserved writings like \u201cGaius Pumidius Diphilus was here,\u201d which had been written as early graffiti. (*) </b> Pliny the Elder died during this event, which buried Herculaneum in a pyroclastic flow. For ten points, name this event in 79 AD that destroyed the Roman city of Pompeii.", "answer": "eruption of Mt.<b> Vesuvius</b> (accept elaborations; accept descriptions of \u201cthe<b> destruction of Pompeii</b> until \u201cHerculaneum\u201d is read, then prompt on it until \u201cPompeii\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This party split into two separate factions after 1956 when its final presidential candidate, Darlington Hoopes, won fewer than 6,000 votes. Walter Lippmann founded the National</b> <b>Party to (+)</b> <b>oppose this party after World War I. Assisting the ARU during the Pullman</b> <b>oppose this party after World War I. Assisting the ARU during the Pullman</b> <b>strike got a candidate from this political party (*)</b> <b>strike got a candidate from this political party (*)</b> imprisoned; that same member was later arrested under the Espionage Act of 1917. For ten points, name this American political party, sponsored by progressives and labor unions, for which Eugene Debs ran for President five times.", "answer": "<b> Socialist</b> Party of America <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>This modern-day country was once the base of the Uskok pirates. Operation</b> <b>Storm was carried out under its first president, Franjo Tudjman [fran-yo tudge-man].</b> <b>This country is home to the port city of (+) Rijeka [ree-ay-ka], once known as Fiume,</b> <b>and the fascist Ustashe party once held power here. Formerly part of (*)</b> Yugoslavia, the southern portion of this country is historically known as Dalmatia. For ten points, name this European country with its capital at Zagreb. ANSWER: Republic of<b> Croatia</b> (or Republika<b> Hrvatska</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}